片名: 查理和巧克力工厂
(金奖券)
(旺卡酥脆惊喜)
(目的地: 伦敦) (目的地: 纽约)
(目的地: 开罗) (目的地: 东京)
制片: 布雷德·葛瑞
制片: 理查·赛纳克
编剧: 约翰·奥古斯特
导演: 提姆·波顿
这是一个平凡小男孩的故事...
This is a story of an ordinary little boy...
他名叫查理·巴格特
named Charlie Bucket.
他并不比别的小孩跑得快 也不比他们强壮或是聪明
He was not faster or stronger or more clever than other children.
他家不富有  没背景 也不是什么皇亲国戚
His family was not rich or powerful or well-connected.
其实  他们家温饱都成问题
In fact, they barely had enough to eat.
但查理是全世界最幸运的小男孩
Charlie Bucket was the luckiest boy in the entire world.
只是他还不知道而已
He just didn't know it yet.
-大家好  -你好
-Evening, Buckets. -Evening.
爸爸
Hi, Dad.
汤快煮好了  老公
Soup's almost ready, darling.
应该没得加菜吧?
Don't suppose there's anything extra to put in, love.
算了 甘蓝菜配甘蓝菜最对味了
Oh, well. Nothing goes better with cabbage than cabbage.
查理...
Charlie...
我找到一样东西 你应该会喜欢
I found something I think you'll like.
查理的父亲在当地牙膏厂上班
Charlie's father worked at the local toothpaste factory.
工作时间很长  薪水却少得可怜...
The hours were long, and the pay was terrible...
但偶尔会有意外的惊喜
yet occasionally, there were unexpected surprises.
这正是我需要的
It's exactly what I need.
那是什么  查理?
What is it, Charlie?
爸爸找到了  正好是我需要的
Dad found it, just the piece I needed.
-是什么啊?  -威利·旺卡的头
-What piece was it? -A head for Willy Wonka.
太好了
Well, how wonderful.
做得很像哦
It's quite a likeness.
-真的吗?  -当然
-You think so? -Think so?
我一看就知道了
I know so.
我亲眼看过威利·旺卡本人
I saw Willy Wonka with my own two eyes.
-我以前在他的工厂上班 -真的吗?
-I used to work for him, you know. -You did?
-真的 -真的
-I did. -He did.
真的
He did.
我喜欢葡萄
I love grapes.
当然  当时的我比现在年轻很多啦
Of course, I was a much younger man in those days.
威利·旺卡原本在樱桃街  开了一家小店
Willy Wonka began with a single store on Cherry Street.
(二十年前)
但全世界的人都想吃他的糖果
But the whole world wanted his candy.
-旺卡先生  -什么事?
-Mr. Wonka. -Yeah?
旺卡巧克力糖不够卖了...
We need more Wonka bars...
-巧克力鸟也没了  -鸟?
and we're out of chocolate birds. -Birds?
鸟
Birds.
好吧  那就多做一点  来
Well, then we'll need to make some more. Here.
嘴巴张开
Now open.
那个人是天才
The man was a genius.
他发明了一个新方法  做出来的巧克力冰淇淋
Did you know he invented a new way of making chocolate ice cream...
不放冰箱  也能好几个小时不融化
so that it stays cold for hours without a freezer?
甚至放在大热天的太阳底下  也不会融化
You can even leave it lying in the sun on a hot day, and it won't go runny.
-不可能啦  -但威利·旺卡做到了
-But that's impossible. -But Willy Wonka did it.
不久之后...
Before long...
(十五年前)
他决定建一座像样的巧克力工厂
he decided to build a proper chocolate factory.
有史以来最大的巧克力工厂
The largest chocolate factory in history.
是别的工厂的五十倍大
Fifty times as big as any other.
爷爷  别讲得那么恶啦
Grandpa, don't make it gross.
跟他说那个印度王子的事 他一定会喜欢的
Tell him about the Indian prince. He'd like to hear about that.
你是说本地治里王子吗?
You mean, Prince Pondicherry?
本地治里王子 写了一封信给旺卡先生
Well, Prince Pondicherry wrote a letter to Mr. Wonka...
请他大老远赶到印度
and asked him to come all the way out to India...
建造一座巨大无比的宫殿 全部都用巧克力做成的
and build him a colossal palace entirely out of chocolate.
(新德里  印度)
要有一百个房间
It will have 100 rooms,
全是巧克力做的 不管是什么巧克力
and everything will be made of either dark or light chocolate.
他向来是说到做到 砖块是巧克力
True to his word, the bricks were chocolate...
混凝土接合剂也是巧克力
and the cement holding them together was chocolate.
所有墙壁和天花板都是巧克力
All the walls and ceilings were made of chocolate as well.
地毯  墙上的画和家具也是
So were the carpets and the pictures and the furniture.
一切都很完美
It is perfect in every way.
对  但持续不了多久 你最好马上开始吃
Yeah, but it won't last long. You better start eating right now.
胡说八道  我才不吃我的宫殿
Oh, nonsense. I will not eat my palace.
我要住在里面
I intend to live in it.
当然是被旺卡先生说中了
But Mr. Wonka was right, of course.
没过多久  有一天烈日当空  热得要命
Soon after this, there came a very hot day with a boiling sun.
王子发了紧急电报 要求重建一座宫殿...
The prince sent an urgent telegram requesting a new palace...
但威利·旺卡自己也遇到了麻烦
but Willy Wonka was facing problems of his own.
其他的巧克力制造商  越来越眼红旺卡
All the other chocolate makers, you see, had grown jealous of Mr. Wonka.
他们开始派间谍进工厂 窃取他的秘密配方
They began sending in spies to steal his secret recipes.
(秘密配方)
菲克尔格鲁伯开始制造 永不融化的冰淇淋
Fickelgruber started making an ice cream that would never melt.
普罗德诺斯生产了 味道永不变淡的口香糖
Prodnose came out with a chewing gum that never lost its flavor.
斯洛格华思也开始做...
Then Slugworth began making candy balloons...
可以吹得好大好大的糖果气球
that you could blow up to incredible sizes.
间谍窃取资料的事件频传...
The thievery got so bad...
有一天  在毫无预警的情况下...
that one day, without warning...
旺卡先生请所有工人回家
Mr. Wonka told every single one of his workers to go home.
他宣布要永远关闭巧克力工厂
He announced that he was closing his chocolate factory forever.
我要永远关闭巧克力工厂了
I'm closing my chocolate factory forever.
对不起
I'm sorry.
可是没有永远关闭  现在又开工了啊
But it didn't close forever. It's open right now.
恩  有时候大人说的永远 只是指很长一段时间
Yes, well, sometimes when grownups say"forever," they mean"a very long time."
比如  我好像永远都在吃甘蓝菜汤
Such as,"I feel like I've eaten nothing but cabbage soup forever."
-岳父  别闹了 -工厂确实关闭了  查理
-Now, Pops. -The factory did close, Charlie.
大家都以为真的会永远关闭
And it seemed like it was going to be closed forever.
结果有一天 我们看到烟囱又冒出烟来了
Then one day we saw smoke rising from the chimneys.
-工厂又恢复运作了 -你又回去上班了吗?
-The factory was back in business. -Did you get your job back?
没有
No.
谁也没有回去上班
No one did.
可是一定有人在里面工作
But there must be people working there.
查理  你回想一下  有没有看到任何人...
Think about it, Charlie. Have you ever seen a single person...
进入工厂或从工厂出来?
going into that factory or coming out of it?
没有  一直是大门深锁
No. The gates are always closed.
那就对了
Exactly.
到底是谁在操作机器呢?
But then, who's running the machines?
-没人知道  -这是一个谜
-Nobody knows, Charlie. -It certainly is a mystery.
没人问过旺卡先生吗?
Hasn't someone asked Mr. Wonka?
没人再见过他了  他也没再出来过
Nobody sees him anymore. He never comes out.
唯一从工厂出来的就只有糖果...
The only thing that comes out of that place is the candy...
都已经包装封箱分配好了
already packed and addressed.
我愿不惜任何代价再进工厂一次...
I'd give anything in the world just to go in one more time...
看看那间不可思议的工厂 现在变成怎样了
and see what's become of that amazing factory.
不可能的  因为你进不去  没人进的去
Well, you won't, because you can't. No one can.
这是一个谜  永远都是一个谜
It's a mystery, and it will always be a mystery.
你那个模型小工厂 是我们唯一能靠近的工厂
That little factory of yours, Charlie, is as close as any of us is ever going to get.
走吧  查理 老人家们该睡觉了
Come on, Charlie. I think it's time we let your grandparents get some sleep.
-晚安  乔治公公  -晚安  查理
-Good night, Grandpa George. -Night, Charlie.
-晚安  -椅子
-Night-night. -Chair.
谢谢你  亲爱的
Thank you, dear.
晚安  约瑟夫爷爷
Night, Grandpa Joe.
晚安  乔治娜婆婆
Good night, Grandma Georgina.
世上没有不可能的事  查理
Nothing's impossible, Charlie.
-晚安  -晚安  查理
-Good night. -Night, Charlie.
祝你好梦
Sleep well.
其实那天晚上 不可能的事就已经开始发生了
Indeed, that very night, the impossible had already been set in motion.
亲爱的世人...
Dear people of the world...
我...威利·旺卡...
I, Willy Wonka...
决定让五个小朋友  来参观我的工厂
have decided to allow five children to visit my factory this year.
另外  其中一个小朋友 还可以赢得大奖...
In addition, one of these children shall receive a special prize...
超乎任何人想像的大奖
beyond anything you could ever imagine.
有五张金奖券...
Five golden tickets have been hidden...
藏在五块普通装旺卡巧克力  不起眼的包装纸里
underneath the ordinary wrapping paper of five ordinary Wonka bars.
这五块巧克力可能在任何地方...
The bars may be anywhere...
(东京  日本)
在任何一个国家的任何城市 任何街道的任何一家商店里
in any shop, in any street, in any town, in any country in the world.
(马拉喀什  摩洛哥)
(纽约)
查理  很令人兴奋吧 拆开巧克力糖的包装纸...
Wouldn't it be something, Charlie, to open a bar of candy...
发现里面有张金奖券
and find a golden ticket inside?
是啊  但我一年只有一块巧克力糖 是生日礼物
I know, but I only get one bar a year, for my birthday.
你生日下礼拜就到了啊
Well, it's your birthday next week.
你和任何人的机会一样多
You have as much chance as anybody does.
胡说八道 找得到金奖券的小孩...
Balderdash. The kids who are going to find the golden tickets...
一定是每天都买巧克力来吃的小孩
are the ones who can afford to buy candy bars every day.
咱们查理一年只有一块  他没机会的拉
Our Charlie gets only one a year. He doesn't have a chance.
查理  每个人都有机会
Everyone has a chance, Charlie.
我说的准没错 找到第一张金奖券的小孩...
Mark my words, the kid who finds the first ticket...
一定是个超级大胖子
will be fat, fat, fat.
奥古塔斯  看这边
Augustus. This way.
(杜塞道夫  德国)
我在吃旺卡巧克力的时候...
I am eating the Wonka bar...
突然吃到不是巧克力的东西...
and I taste something that is not chocolate...
也不是椰果...
or coconut...
也不是胡桃  也不是花生酱...
or walnut or peanut butter...
也不是牛轧糖...
or nougat...
也不是脆果糖或焦糖  也不是巧克力糖霜
or butter brittle or caramel or sprinkles.
于是我看了一眼...
So I look...
就发现金奖券了
and I find the golden ticket.
奥古塔斯  你怎么庆祝的?
Augustus, how did you celebrate?
我又吃更多的糖果
I eat more candy.
我们早就知道 奥古塔斯会找到金奖券
We knew Augustus would find the golden ticket.
他每天都吃好多糖果...
He eats so many candy bars a day...
不可能连一张金奖券都找不到
that it was not possible for him not to find one.
很不错  奥古塔斯
Yes, it is good, Augustus.
出现第一张金奖券  还剩下四张...
Golden ticket claimed and four more...
我就说是个大胖子嘛
Told you it'd be a porker.
真讨人厌的小孩
What a repulsive boy.
只剩下四张金奖券了
Only four golden tickets left.
既然有人找到一张  大家一定会越来越疯狂
Now that they've found one, things will really get crazy.
每种形状  大小  及色彩
Of every shape, size and hue.
(英国白金汉郡)
维露卡  麻烦你拼一下  好吗
Veruca. Can you spell that for us, please?
维-露-卡 维露卡·索尔特
V-E-R-U-C-A. Veruca Salt.
我的小维露卡一说她想要金奖券...
As soon as my little Veruca told me she had to have one of these golden tickets...
我就把买得到的旺卡巧克力 全都买下来
I started buying all the Wonka bars I could lay my hands on.
成千上万块  数以百计
Thousands of them. Hundreds of thousands.
我是从事坚果业 所以我就告诉工人们
I'm in the nut business, you see. So I say to my workers:
各位女士早安 从现在起暂停剥花生壳...
Morning, ladies. From now on, you can stop shelling peanuts...
改拆这些巧克力的包装纸
and start shelling the wrappers off these chocolate bars instead.
过了三天  还是没找到 真是太糟糕了
Three days went by, and we had no luck.  Oh, it was terrible.
我的小维露卡一天比一天生气
My Veruca got more and more upset each day.
我的金奖券呢?
Where's my golden ticket?
我要我的金奖券
I want my golden ticket.
各位  我最讨厌看到我的宝贝女儿不开心
Well, gentlemen, I just hated to see my little girl feeling unhappy like that.
我发誓不找到金奖券绝不罢休
I vowed I would keep searching until I could give her what she wanted.
结果终于让我找到了一张
And finally, I found her a ticket.
(索尔特坚果公司)
爸爸  我还要一匹小马
Daddy, I want another pony.
她比那个胖小子更讨人厌
She's even worse than the fat boy.
我觉得不太公平 她不是自己发现金奖券的
I don't think that was really fair. She didn't find the ticket herself.
别担心  查理  那人把她女儿宠坏了
Don't worry about it, Charlie. That man spoils his daughter.
像那样宠坏小孩 是不会有好下场的
And no good ever comes from spoiling a child like that.
查理  我和你妈希望你...
Charlie, Mum and I thought...
今晚就拆生日礼物
maybe you wanna open your birthday present tonight.
拿去吧
Here you are.
(一流开心牛奶巧克力软糖)
我等明天早上再拆好了
Maybe I should wait till morning.
-门儿都没有  -岳父
-Like hell. -Pop.
我们加起来381岁了  别想叫我们等
All together, we're 381 years old. We don't wait.
查理  就算没找到...
Now, Charlie, you mustn't feel too disappointed...
也不要觉得太失望...
you know, if you don't get the...
无论如何  你还有巧克力吃
Whatever happens, you'll still have the candy.
好了
Ah, well.
没戏唱了
That's that.
-我们分着吃吧  -不行
-We'll share it. -Oh, no, Charlie.
这是你的生日礼物
Not your birthday present.
这是我的巧克力 我想给谁吃就给谁吃
It's my candy bar, and I'll do what I want with it.
谢谢你
Thank you, darling.
Thank you, Charlie.
愿神佑你
Bless you.
好  看看是谁找到的
All right, let's see who found it.
第三张金奖券的得主 是紫罗兰·博雷加德小姐
"The third ticket was found by Miss Violet Beauregarde."
(乔治亚州  亚特兰大市)
这些只是我的紫罗兰 赢得的263座奖杯的一部分
These are just some of the 263 trophies and medals my Violet has won.
我平常喜欢嚼口香糖 但我一听到金奖券的事...
I'm a gum chewer mostly, but when I heard about these ticket things...
就暂时不买口香糖  改买巧克力
I laid off the gum, switched to candy bars.
她是个冲劲十足的小女孩 不知道是遗传谁的
She's just a driven young woman. I don't know where she gets it.
我是嚼口香糖的世界冠军
I'm the Junior World Champion Gum Chewer.
我嘴里嚼的这片口香糖...
This piece of gum I'm chewing right now...
已经整整嚼了三个月 刷新了世界纪录
I've been working on for three months solid. That's a record.
当然  我也有不少战利品 多半是甩指挥棒得来的
Of course, I did have my share of trophies, mostly baton.
上面写着有个小朋友能得到大奖 别的小朋友都得不到
So it says that one kid's gonna get this special prize, better than all the rest.
我才不管其他四个人是谁 得大奖的小孩一定是我
I don't care who those other four are. That kid, it's gonna be me.
告诉他们为什么  紫罗兰
Tell them why, Violet.
因为我天生是赢家
Because I'm a winner.
真讨人厌的女孩
What a beastly girl.
卑鄙下流
Despicable.
你知不知道我们在说啥
You don't know what we're talking about.
蜻蜓吗?
Dragonflies?
等一下  有最新消息
But wait, this is just in.
第四张金奖券找到了 是一名叫麦克·蒂维的男孩
The fourth golden ticket has been found by a boy called Mike Teavee.
(科罗拉多州  丹佛市)
只要从制造日期来推算就好了...
All you had to do was track the manufacturing dates...
再加上天气的影响 还有日经指数的导数值
offset by weather and the derivative of the Nikkei Index.
就连智障都算得出来
A retard could figure it out.
我经常听不懂他在讲什么
Most of the time I don't know what he's talking about.
这年头的小孩知道太多高科技了...
You know, kids these days, what with all the technology...
去死!  去死!
Die! Die! Die!
他们的童年应该不会太长
Doesn't seem like they stay kids very long.
我只要买一块巧克力就够了
In the end, I only had to buy one candy bar.
-好不好吃?  -不知道
-And how did it taste? -I don't know.
我讨厌巧克力
I hate chocolate.
那你干嘛要去巧克力工厂? 你这个忘恩负义的...
Well, it's a good thing you're going to a chocolate factory, you ungrateful little...
问题是 谁会找到最后一张金奖...
That question is, who will be the winner of the last gold...?
-爸爸?  -什么事?
-Dad? -Yes, Charlie?
你怎么没去上班?
Why aren't you at work?
牙膏工厂希望我能休息一阵子
Oh, well, the toothpaste factory thought they'd give me a bit of time off.
像暑假一样?
Like summer vacation?
对  就是那样
Sure. Something like that.
其实他根本不是放什么假
In fact, it wasn't like a vacation at all.
糖果卖得好 结果蛀牙的人就变多了...
The upswing in candy sales had led to a rise in cavities...
牙膏的销售量也随之提升
which led to a rise in toothpaste sales.
工厂赚了大钱 就决定要现代化...
With the extra money, the factory had decided to modernize...
结果巴格特先生失业了
eliminating Mr. Bucket's job.
我们原本就已经三餐不继
We were barely making ends meet as it was.
你会找到新工作的
You'll find another job.
在此之前我就...我就把汤稀释一点
Until then, I'll just...Well, I'll just thin down the soup a little more.
放心吧  巴格特先生 我们会转运的
Don't worry, Mr. Bucket, our luck will change.
我有信心
I know it.
查理
Charlie.
我的私房钱
My secret hoard.
咱们爷俩再试一次手气  看看...
You and I are going to have one more fling...
能不能找到最后一张金奖券
at finding that last ticket.
你确定要把钱花在这上面?
You sure you want to spend your money on that?
我当然确定  拿去吧
Of course I'm sure. Here.
跑去最近的商店...
Run down to the nearest store...
看到第一块旺卡巧克力就买下来
and buy the first Wonka candy bar you see.
直接拿回家 我们一起拆包装纸
Bring it straight back, and we'll open it together.
真是个乖孩子
Such a good boy, really.
真是个乖...
Such a good...
爷爷?
Grandpa?
-你睡着了  -你买到了吗?
-You fell asleep. -Have you got it?
要从哪一端开始拆?
Which end should we open first?
速战速决  像撕OK绷一样
Just do it quick, like a Band-Aid.
你知不知道有个俄国小孩 找到最后一张金奖券了?
Did you see that some kid in Russia found the last golden ticket?
对  今天的早报有登
Yes, it was in the paper this morning.
乖狗狗 来吧  乔治  乖狗狗
Good boy. Come on, George. Good boy.
请给我一块旺卡一流开心牛奶巧克力软糖
One Wonka Whipple-Scrumptious Fudgemallow Delight, please.
好的  拿去吧
Okay. Here you go.
(俄国的金奖券是假的 还剩一张金奖券)
那些人真胆大
The nerve of some people.
对啊 仿造金奖券?  别傻了
I know. Forging a ticket. Come on.
那是金奖券耶
It's a golden ticket.
你找到旺卡的最后一张金奖券
You found Wonka's last golden ticket.
而且是在我店里买的
In my shop too!
听着 我跟你买  我给你五十元  外加一辆脚踏车
Listen. I'll buy it from you. I'll give you $50 and a new bicycle.
你疯了吗?  我出五百元买你的金奖券
Are you crazy? I'd give him $500 for that ticket.
五百元把金奖券卖给我吧
You wanna sell me your ticket for $500, young man?
够了  别烦这位小朋友
That's enough of that. Leave the kid alone.
听着  千万不要给任何人 直接拿着回家  懂吗?
Listen. Don't let anyone have it. Take it straight home, you understand?
谢谢你
Thank you.
妈!  爸!
Mom! Dad!
我找到了!
I found it!
最后一张金奖券!  是我的!
The last golden ticket! It's mine!
拿去
Here.
大声念出来  看看上面写什么
Read it aloud. Let's hear exactly what it says.
欢迎你  找到金奖券的幸运儿 威利·旺卡先生祝福你
"Greetings to you, the lucky finder of this golden ticket, from Mr. Willy Wonka.
我要热情地握你的手  邀请你来我的工厂...
I shake you warmly by the hand. For now, I do invite you to come to my factory...
当我整整一天的贵宾
and be my guest for one whole day."
我  威利·旺卡 将亲自带你们参观工厂...
"I, Willy Wonka, will conduct you around the factory myself...
带你们看遍每个细节
showing you everything there is to see."
等到参观完毕要离开时...
"Afterwards, when it is time to leave...
你可以载走满满好几卡车...
you will be escorted home by a procession of large trucks...
足够让你吃一辈子的巧克力
each one filled with all the chocolate you could ever eat."
记住  五个小朋友当中 有一位将独得大奖...
"And remember, one of you lucky five children will receive an extra prize...
超乎你最疯狂的想像之外
beyond your wildest imagination.
请遵照以下的指示
Now, here are your instructions."
请在二月一日 上午十点整到工厂门口
"On the 1st of February, you must come to the factory gates at 10 a.m. Sharp.
你可以带一位家人随行照顾
You're allowed to bring one member of your family to look after you.
到时候见了 威利·旺卡
Until then, Willy Wonka."
二月一日
The 1st of February.
-就是明天耶 -那片刻不容缓了  查理
-But that's tomorrow. -Then there's not a moment to lose.
快去洗脸...梳头...洗手...刷牙...清鼻子
Wash your face, comb your hair, scrub your hands, brush your teeth, blow your nose.
-还要换掉那条脏裤子 -我们现在要保持冷静
-And get that mud off your pants. -Now we must all try and keep very calm.
首先要决定的是
First thing that we have to decide is this:
谁来陪查理去参观工厂
Who is going with Charlie to the factory?
我去  我带他去 交给我就对了
I will. I'll take him. You leave it to me.
怎样?  你不觉得你应该去吗?
How about you, dear? Don't you think you ought to go?
约瑟夫爷爷好像比我们任何人  知道得多...
Well, Grandpa Joe seems to know more about it than we do, and...
当然前提是他身体负荷得了
Provided, of course, he feels well enough.
不行  我们不去了
No. We're not going.
有个阿姨要花五百元买金奖券
A woman offered me $500 for the ticket.
一定还有人出价更高
I bet someone else would pay more.
我们需要的是钱  不是巧克力
We need the money more than we need the chocolate.
小伙子  过来
Young man, come here.
外头的钱多得是
There's plenty of money out there.
每天都有新钞在印
They print more every day.
但这张金奖券...
But this ticket...
全世界只有五张而已...
there's only five of them in the whole world...
以后也不会再有了
and that's all there's ever going to be.
只有傻瓜才会放弃金奖券 要钱那种俗气的东西
Only a dummy would give this up for something as common as money.
你是傻瓜吗?
Are you a dummy?
不是
No, sir.
那就去换掉那条脏裤子 你要去参观工厂了
Then get that mud off your pants. You've got a factory to go to.
爸爸  我要进去
Daddy, I want to go in.
才9点59分  甜心
It's 9:59, sweetheart.
叫时间过快一点啦
Make time go faster.
你觉得旺卡先生会认出你吗?
Do you think Mr. Wonka will recognize you?
很难说  事隔多年了
Hard to say. It's been years.
专心得大奖  紫罗兰
Eyes on the prize, Violet.
专心得大奖
Eyes on the prize.
请进
Please enter.
向前走
Come forward.
关上大门
Close the gates.
亲爱的贵宾...
Dear visitors...
很荣幸各位来参观我的小工厂
it is my great pleasure to welcome you to my humble factory.
我是谁呢?
And who am I?
这个嘛...
Well...
威利·旺卡  威利·旺卡
Willy Wonka, Willy Wonka
了不起的巧克力制造商
The amazing chocolatier
威利·旺卡  威利·旺卡
Willy Wonka, Willy Wonka
大家为他欢呼吧  万岁!
Everybody give a cheer! Hooray!
他谦虚  机灵又聪明
He's modest, clever and so smart
想不爱现也难
He barely can restrain it
而且又乐善好施
With so much generosity
根本不可能掩饰
There is no way to contain it!
掩饰...
To contain it To contain, to contain, to contain!
万岁!
Hooray!
威利·旺卡  威利·旺卡
Willy Wonka, Willy Wonka
你们待会儿就要见到他
He's the one that you're about to meet
威利·旺卡  威利·旺卡
Willy Wonka, Willy Wonka
他是个天才  没人赢得过他
He's the genius who just can't be beat
他是魔术师和巧克力奇才
The magician and the chocolate wiz
有史以来最了不起的人
The best darn guy who ever lived
他就是威利·旺卡!
Willy Wonka, here he is!
巧克力奇才
The amazing chocolatier
很精彩吧?
Wasn't that just magnificent?
我本来还担心中间会有点怪
I was worried it was getting a little dodgy in the middle part,
可是那个结尾...
but then that finale...
你是谁?
Who are you?
-他是威利·旺卡  -真的吗?
-He's Willy Wonka. -Really?
星光早安
"Good morning, starshine.
大地向你打招呼
The Earth says hello."
亲爱的贵宾  大家好
"Dear guests, greetings.
欢迎来到工厂 我要热情地握你的手
Welcome to the factory. I shake you warmly by the hand.
我叫威利·旺卡
My name is Willy Wonka."
那你不是应该在那上面吗?
Then shouldn't you be up there?
坐在上面就看不到表演了 对吧  小女孩?
I couldn't very well watch the show from up there, now, could I, little girl?
旺卡先生  不知道你记不记得我...
Mr. Wonka, I don't know if you'll remember me...
我以前在贵工厂上班
but I used to work here in the factory.
你是爱剽窃别人的糖果商 雇来的间谍...
Were you one of those despicable spies who tried to steal...
偷走我毕生的心血 卖给人家的人吗?
my life's work and sell it to parasitic, copycat, candy-making cads?
不是
No, sir.
那就好  欢迎你回来
Then wonderful. Welcome back.
我们快开始吧
Let's get a move on, kids.
你不想知道我们的名字吗?
Don't you want to know our names?
我觉得没必要耶 快走吧  有太多东西要看了
Can't imagine how it would matter. Come quickly. Far too much to see.
外套随便丢就行了
Just drop your coats anywhere.
-旺卡先生  室内很热耶 -什么?
-Mr. Wonka? Sure is toasty in here. -What?
室内要保持温暖 因为我的员工都习惯热带气候
I have to keep it warm in here. My workers are used to an extremely hot climate.
他们受不了寒冷
They just can't stand the cold.
什么员工?
Who are the workers?
待会儿就知道了  现在...
All in good time. Now...
旺卡先生  我是紫罗兰·博雷加德
Mr. Wonka, I'm Violet Beauregarde.
-我才不在乎 -你应该要在乎
-I don't care. -Well, you should care.
因为赢得大奖的人会是我
Because I'm gonna win the special prize at the end.
你看起来很有自信  自信很重要
Well, you do seem confident, and confidence is key.
我是维露卡·索尔特  幸会
I'm Veruca Salt. It's very nice to meet you, sir.
我以为维露卡...
I always thought a verruca was a type of wart...
是脚底长的一种疣
you got on the bottom of your foot.
我是奥古塔斯·格卢普 我很爱吃你的巧克力
I am Augustus Gloop. I love your chocolate.
看得出来  我也很喜欢
I can see that. So do I.
没想到我们有这么多共同点
I never expected to have so much in common.
你是麦克·蒂维
You. You're Mike Teavee.
那个坏了我好事的小魔鬼
You're the little devil who cracked the system.
还有你 你纯粹是运气好吧
And you. Well, you're just lucky to be here, aren't you?
其他几位想必是他们的...
And the rest of you must be their...
-家长?  -对
-Parents. -Yeah.
爸爸和妈妈
Moms and dads.
爸爸?
Dad?
爸?
Papa?
好了  我们继续走
Okay, then. Let's move along.
-想不想吃巧克力? -好啊
-Would you like some chocolate? -Sure.
那你要自己带啊
Then you should've brought some.
-我们当好朋友吧 -最好的朋友
-Let's be friends. -Best friends.
这个房间很重要
An important room, this.
-毕竟这是巧克力工厂 -为什么门这么小?
-After all, it is a chocolate factory. -Then why is the door so small?
这样浓郁的巧克力香味 才不会散出去啊
That's to keep all the great big chocolaty flavor inside.
现在...小心点  亲爱的孩子们
Now, do be careful, my dear children.
别昏了头
Don't lose your heads.
别兴奋过度
Don't get overexcited.
尽量保持冷静
Just keep very calm.
好漂亮
It's beautiful.
什么?
What?
对  是很漂亮
Oh, yeah, it's very beautiful.
河里的每一滴巧克力...
Every drop of the river...
都是最高品质的热融巧克力
is hot, melted chocolate of the finest quality.
瀑布是最重要的关键
The waterfall is most important.
用瀑布来混合巧克力
Mixes the chocolate.
搅拌均匀 让巧克力滑溜又顺口
Churns it up. Makes it light and frothy.
对了...
By the way...
全世界没有别的工厂  用瀑布来混合巧克力
no other factory in the world mixes its chocolate by waterfall, my dear children.
这点我可以向你们保证
And you can take that to the bank.
各位
People.
那些管子...
Those pipes...
会吸取巧克力 输送到工厂内的各个角落
suck up the chocolate and carry it away all over the factory.
每小时好几千加仑 没错
Thousands of gallons an hour. Yeah.
喜欢这片草地吗?  抓一把来吃
And do you like my meadow? Try some of my grass.
你们就吃一点吧 这是又好吃又好看
Please have a blade. Please do. It's so delectable and so darn good-looking.
草也可以吃?
You can eat the grass?
当然
Of course you can.
这个房间里的每样东西都能吃
Everything in this room is eatable.
就连我也可以吃
Even I'm eatable.
不过我们不是食人族啦...
But that is called cannibalism, my dear children...
文明社会是不容许人吃人的
and is, in fact, frowned upon in most societies.
是啊
Yeah.
尽情享用吧
Enjoy.
去啊 快去啊
Go on. Scoot, scoot.
儿子
Son.
拜托别闹了
Please.
爸  他说"尽情"耶
Dad, he said, "Enjoy."
何必这么坚持?  干嘛不换片新的?
Why hold on to it? Why not start a new piece?
换了  我就不是冠军 而是个失败者  像你一样
Because then I wouldn't be a champion. I'd be a loser, like you.
爸爸  看那边
Daddy, look over there.
那是什么?
What is it?
是一个小矮人
It's a little person.
在那里  瀑布旁边
Over there, by the waterfall.
-有两个耶  -不只两个
-There's two of them. -There's more than two.
-他们从哪儿来的?  -他们是谁?
-Where do they come from? -Who are they?
他们是真人吗?
Are they real people?
他们当然是真人 他们是奥柏伦柏人
Of course they're real people. They're Oompa-Loompas.
-奥柏伦柏人?  -直接从伦柏地进口的
-Oompa-Loompas? -Imported, direct from Loompaland.
-没这个地方  -什么?
-There's no such place. -What?
旺卡先生  我教高中地理  我跟你说...
Mr. Wonka, I teach high-school geography, and I'm here to tell you...
那你应该清楚  那个地方太可怕了
Well, then you'll know all about it, and, oh, what a terrible country it is.
整片土地上只有茂密的丛林...
The whole place is nothing but thick jungles...
到处都是全世界最危险的怪兽
infested by the most dangerous beasts in the entire world.
独角兽和怪鼻兽 还有可怕又邪恶的丑怪兽
Hornswogglers and snozzwangers and those terrible, wicked whangdoodles.
我去伦柏地找异国风糖果口味
I went to Loompaland looking for exotic new flavors for candy.
结果却...
Instead...
找到奥柏伦柏人
I found the Oompa-Loompas.
他们住在树屋里 躲避地面上的凶猛怪兽
They lived in tree houses to escape from the fierce creatures who lived below.
奥柏伦柏人只能吃非常难吃的绿毛虫
The Oompa-Loompas ate nothing but green caterpillars, which tasted revolting.
他们一直找别的东西...
The Oompa-Loompas looked for other things...
来拌毛虫糊  看能不能好吃一点
to mash up with the caterpillars to make them taste better:
红甲虫  梆梆树皮
Red beetles, the bark of the bong-bong tree.
全都不好吃...
All of them beastly...
但比光吃毛毛虫好吃多啦
but not quite so beastly as the caterpillars.
但他们最想吃的食物是可可豆
But the food they longed for the most was the cocoa bean.
每个奥柏伦柏人一年能找到 三四颗可可豆就算幸运了
An Oompa-Loompa was lucky if he found three or four cocoa beans a year.
他们超爱吃可可豆
But, oh, how they craved them.
他们整天只想着可可豆
All they'd ever think about was cocoa beans.
可可豆是巧克力的原料 于是我跟酋长说...
The cocoa bean is the thing from which chocolate is made, so I told the chief:
(搬来我的工厂住吧)
(你们想吃多少可可豆都行)
(我也可用可可豆当你们的工资)
他们都是勤劳的工人
They are such wonderful workers.
但我警告你们  他们很顽皮
I feel I must warn you, though, they are rather mischievous.
一天到晚恶作剧
Always making jokes.
奥古塔斯  千万别那样做
Augustus, my child, that is not a good thing you do!
小男孩
Hey, little boy.
不要用手去碰我的巧克力
My chocolate must be untouched by human hands.
他会溺死的
He'll drown.
他不会游泳
He can't swim.
快救他!
Save him!
奥古塔斯!  不!
Augustus! No!
奥古塔斯!
Augustus!
奥古塔斯  小心!
Augustus, watch out!
他被吸上去了
There he goes.
快来人  救命啊!
Call the fire brigade!
那根管子居然够粗耶
It's a wonder how that pipe is big enough.
不够粗啦 他慢下来了
It isn't big enough. He's slowing down.
他会卡住的
He's gonna stick.
已经卡住了
I think he has.
整根管子都被他塞住了
He's blocked the whole pipe.
你们看  奥柏伦柏人
Look. The Oompa-Loompas.
他们在干嘛?
What are they doing?
他们应该是想唱歌给我们听 这是很特别的场合
They're going to treat us to a little song. It is quite a special occasion.
他们很久没观众了
They haven't had a fresh audience in many a moon.
奥古塔斯·格卢普...
Augustus Gloop, Augustus Gloop...
那个贪吃的大傻瓜
The great big, greedy nincompoop
奥古塔斯·格卢普  又肥又皮  贪婪可恶又幼稚
Augustus Gloop, so big and vile So greedy, foul and infantile
我们叫道: 时机已成熟
"Come on!" we cried "The time is ripe
把他弄到玻璃管里去
To send him shooting up the pipe!"
不过亲爱的小朋友们  不必害怕
But don't, dear children, be alarmed
奥古塔斯·格卢普不会出事
Augustus Gloop will not be harmed
当然  我们必须承认
Although, of course, we must admit
他将有不少改变
He will be altered quite a bit
轮子慢慢地转了一下又一下
Slowly, wheels go round and round
齿轮开始又磨又压...
And cogs begin to grind and pound...
赞啊!  表演得真棒
Bravo! Well done!
他们很可爱  很讨人喜欢吧?
Aren't they delightful? Aren't they charming?
-这段歌舞好像是彩排好的 -他们好像知道会发生什么事
-I do say, that all seemed rather rehearsed. -Like they knew it was gonna happen.
少胡说八道了
Oh, poppycock.
我儿子呢?  那根管子通往哪里?
Where is my son? Where does that pipe go to?
那根管子直通另一个房间...
That pipe, it just so happens to lead...
那个房间是制造最美味的...
directly to the room where I make delicious...
草莓牛奶巧克力夹心软糖
strawberry-flavored, chocolate-coated fudge.
那他就要被做成 草莓牛奶巧克力夹心软糖
Then he will be made into strawberry-flavored, chocolate-coated fudge.
在世界各地称斤论两的卖了
They'll be selling him by the pound all over the world?
不行  我绝对不允许 那一定很难吃
No. I wouldn't allow it. The taste would be terrible.
你能想像...奥古塔斯口味的巧克力糖吗?
Can you imagine Augustus-flavored, chocolate-coated Gloop?
没人会买的
No one would buy it.
请你带格卢普太太去软糖间
I want you to take Mrs. Gloop up to the Fudge Room, okay?
帮忙找她儿子
Help her find her son.
拿一根长棍子 在搅拌巧克力的木桶里探探看  懂吗
Take a long stick and start poking around in the big chocolate-mixing barrel, okay?
旺卡先生?
Mr. Wonka?
奥柏伦柏人唱的歌 怎会有奥古塔斯的名字? 除非他们...
Why would Augustus' name already be in the Oompa-Loompa song, unless...?
即兴演出很简单 谁都会表演
Improvisation is a parlor trick. Anyone can do it.
小女孩  说点什么吧
You, little girl. Say something.
-随便什么都好 -口香糖
-Anything. -Chewing gum.
口香糖实在恶心 口香糖我最唾弃
Chewing gum is really gross Chewing gum, I hate the most
看吧?  就是这样啊
See? Exactly the same.
才不一样呢
No, it isn't.
你不该碎碎念
You really shouldn't mumble.
因为你说的话我一个字也听不懂
Because I can't understand a word you're saying.
现在...继续参观吧
Now, on with the tour.
-奥柏伦柏人真的是在开玩笑吗 -当然是在开玩笑
-Are the Oompa-Loompas really joking? -Of course they're joking.
那个孩子不会有事的
That boy will be fine.
有什么好笑的?
What's so funny?
应该是吃了太多可可豆吧
I think it's from all those doggone cocoa beans.
对了  你们知不知道  巧克力有一种成份...
Hey, by the way, did you guys know that chocolate contains a property...
能刺激脑内啡的分泌 给人恋爱般的愉悦感觉?
that triggers the release of endorphins? Gives one the feeling of being in love.
这样啊
You don't say.
上船啰
All aboard.
前进!
Onward!
来吧
Here.
喝一点  对你有好处 你看起来好像快饿死了
Try some of this. It'll do you good. You look starved to death.
-好好喝哦 -因为这是用瀑布搅拌的
-It's great. -That's because it's mixed by waterfall.
瀑布是最重要的关键
The waterfall is most important.
混合巧克力  搅拌均匀 让巧克力滑溜又顺口
Mixes the chocolate, churns it up, makes it light and frothy.
-对了  全世界没有别的工厂... -你已经说过了
-By the way, no other factory in the world...-You already said that.
-你们都很矮哦 -对  我们是小孩啊
-You're all quite short, aren't you? -Well, yeah. We're children.
那不是理由  我就从没像你那么矮
Well, that's no excuse. I was never as short as you.
-你小时候也一样啦 -才没有  你知道为什么吗?
-You were once. -Was not. Know why?
因为我随时都记得戴上帽子
Because I distinctly remember putting a hat on top of my head.
不像你手那么短  永远够不到头
Look at your short, little arms. You could never reach.
你记不记得小时候的事?
Do you even remember what it was like being a kid?
当然记得
Oh, boy, do I.
是吗?
Do I?
其实威利·旺卡已经好多年 没想起小时候的事了
In fact, Willy Wonka hadn't thought about his childhood for years.
不给糖就捣蛋!
Trick or treat!
来的是谁啊?
Who do we have here?
露西  薇洛妮卡  泰伦斯
Ruthie, Veronica, Terrance.
那个披着白布的是谁?
And who's that under the sheet?
原来是小威利·旺卡
Little Willy Wonka.
威利·旺卡的父亲是城里 最有名的牙医...
Willy Wonka was the son of the city's most famous dentist...
威尔伯·旺卡
Wilbur Wonka.
(威尔伯·旺卡牙医诊所)
来...
Now...
看看今年用什么来害人
let's see what the damage is this year, shall we?
牛奶糖
Caramels.
吃这个会卡在牙套上  对吧?
They'd get stuck in your braces, wouldn't they?
棒棒糖
Lollipops.
应该叫它"插在棒子上的蛀牙"
Ought to be called "cavities on a stick."
然后还有这些...
Then we have all this...
这一大堆...
All this...
巧克力
chocolate.
我上星期才看到一篇报导 那是一本重要的医学期刊
You know, just last week, I was reading in a very important medical journal
报导指出有些小孩对巧克力过敏
that some children are allergic to chocolate.
吃了以后鼻子会痒
Makes their noses itch.
说不定我不会过敏
Maybe I'm not allergic.
让我吃一小块看看
I could try a piece.
真的吗?
Really?
何必冒这个险呢?
But why take a chance?
旺卡先生?
Mr. Wonka? Mr. Wonka?
-旺卡先生  我们要过隧道了 -对了
-We're headed for a tunnel. -Oh, yeah.
全速前进
Full speed ahead.
-他们怎么看得到前面的路? -他们看不到
-How can they see where they're going? -They can't.
他们完全不知道船往哪儿去
There's no knowing where they're going.
开灯!
Switch on the lights!
各位  注意看
People, keep an eye out.
我们会经过几个重要的房间
We're passing some very important rooms here.
(纯奶油)
(咖啡奶油)
(头发奶油)
头发奶油是做什么用的?
What do you use hair cream for?
头发保湿用的啊
To lock in moisture.
-打泡奶油 -答对了
-Whipped cream. -Precisely.
这样做没道理啊
That doesn't make sense.
告诉你吧  小女孩...
For your information, little girl...
没用鞭子一打再打 就不算是打泡奶油
whipped cream isn't whipped cream at all unless it's been whipped with whips.
这是众所周知的
Everybody knows that.
(果冻豆)
停船  我带你们去一个地方
Stop the boat. I wanna show you guys something.
(发明室)
这是全工厂最重要的一个房间
Now, this is the most important room in the entire factory.
各位  尽情参观吧 但千万别伸手摸
Now, everyone, enjoy yourselves, but just don't touch anything.
懂吗?  去吧
Okay? Go on.
快去啊
Go on, scoot.
旺卡先生  这是什么?
Hey, Mr. Wonka, what's this?
我示范给你看
Let me show you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
这是永远吃不完的石头弹子糖
These are Everlasting Gobstoppers.
专门给零用钱很少的小孩吃
They're for children who are given very little allowance.
你可以含着一整年 永远不会变小
You can suck on it all year, and it'll never get any smaller.
-很棒吧?  -像口香糖一样
-Isn't that neat? -It's like gum.
不对  口香糖要嚼
No. Gum is for chewing.
若想嚼这种石头弹子糖...
If you tried chewing one of these Gobstoppers...
你的小牙齿会碎光光
you'd break all your little teeth off.
但真的是好吃极了
But they sure do taste terrific.
这是生发太妃糖
And this is Hair Toffee.
只要吃了这种糖果...
You suck down one of these little boogers...
过了半个小时之后...
and in exactly half an hour...
你会开始长出全新的头发
a brand-new crop of hair will grow out over the top of your little noggin.
还有八字胡和落腮胡
And a mustache. And a beard.
-谁要长落腮胡啊?  -恩...
-Who wants a beard? -Well...
披头族就会啊 民谣歌手和机车骑士
beatniks, for one. Folk singers and motorbike riders.
还有嬉皮 爵士风  超酷超正点 霹雳赞的帅猫
You know, all those hip, jazzy, super-cool, neat, keen and groovy cats.
酷到变冰块了  你们懂吗?
It's in the fridge, daddy-o. Are you hep to the jive?
听得懂我说的话吗?  你们一定懂
Can you dig what I'm laying down? I knew you could.
来握个手吧  老兄
Slide me some skin, soul brother.
可惜混合的比例没有很好
Unfortunately, the mixture isn't right yet.
昨天有个奥柏伦柏人试吃了 结果他...
Because an Oompa-Loompa tried some yesterday, and, well, he...
你今天好吗?
How are you today?
你看起来好极了
You look great.
你们看这个
Watch this.
就这样吗?
You mean that's it?
你知不知道那是什么?
Do you even know what "it" is?
-那是口香糖 -答对了
-It's gum. -Yeah.
这是全宇宙最不可思议 足以轰动世界的口香糖
It's a stick of the most amazing and sensational gum in the whole universe.
你们知道为什么吗?
Know why? Know why?
因为吃了这片口香糖 就等于吃下三道菜的一餐
Because this gum is a full three-course dinner all by itself.
谁会想吃啊?
Why would anyone want that?
不需要厨房  也不必煮饭了
It will be the end of all kitchens and all cooking.
只要吃一片旺卡的神奇口香糖...
Just a little strip of Wonka's magic chewing gum and that is all you will...
早餐  午餐和晚餐就都解决了
ever need at breakfast, lunch and dinner.
这片口香糖结合了 蕃茄汤  烤牛肉和蓝莓派
This piece of gum happens to be tomato soup, roast beef and blueberry pie.
好像很好吃耶
It sounds great.
-好像怪怪的 -好像很适合我
-It sounds weird. -It sounds like my kind of gum.
你最好别吃 还有一两个地方有点...
I'd rather you didn't. There are still some things that are...
我是嚼口香糖的世界冠军 我什么也不怕
I'm the world-record holder in chewing gum. I'm not afraid of anything.
-好不好吃?  -真是不可思议
-How is it, honey? -It's amazing!
我感觉蕃茄汤流进我喉咙里
Tomato soup. I can feel it running down my throat.
对啦  快吐出来
Yeah. Spit it out.
-小姐  我觉得你最好... -味道变了
-Young lady, I think you'd better...-It's changing.
烤牛肉  还有附烤马铃薯
Roast beef, with baked potato.
外皮酥脆  加了牛油
Crispy skin and butter.
继续嚼
Keep chewing.
我的宝贝女儿是全世界第一个吃口香糖大餐的人
My little girl's gonna be the first person to have a chewing-gum meal.
我只是有点担心...
Yeah. I'm just a little concerned about the...
蓝莓派和冰淇淋
Blueberry pie and ice cream!
-那个部分 -她的鼻子怎么了?
-That part. -What's happening to her nose?
变成蓝色了
It's turning blue.
你的鼻子都变紫了
Your whole nose has gone purple.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
紫罗兰  你变成紫罗兰色了
Violet, you're turning violet.
-怎么回事? -我早说过还没完全做好嘛
-What's happening? -Well, I told you I hadn't quite got it right.
因为到了甜点就会怪怪的
Because it goes a little funny when it gets to the dessert.
都是蓝莓派惹的祸
It's the blueberry pie that does it.
真是太对不起了
I'm terribly sorry.
妈妈?  我怎么了?
Mother? What's happening to me?
她胀起来了
She's swelling up.
像蓝莓一样
Like a blueberry.
有二十个奥柏伦柏人试吃过了 每一个都变成蓝莓
I've tried it on, like, 20 Oompa-Loompas, and each one ended up as a blueberry.
真是太奇怪了
It's just weird.
蓝莓不能当我女儿
But I can't have a blueberry as a daughter.
她要怎么比赛?
How is she supposed to compete?
可以参加农产品大赛
You could put her in a county fair.
好啊
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
仔细听好  注意听
Listen close, and listen hard
紫罗兰·博雷加德的故事
To the tale of Violet Beauregarde
这个温柔的小女孩看不见错误
This gentle girl She sees no wrong
从早到晚嚼口香糖
In chewing, chewing, chewing, chewing
Chewing, chewing all day long
从早到晚嚼口香糖
是啊
Yeah
她这样不停地嚼啊嚼
She goes on chewing till, at last
最后由于肌肉变得特别发达
Her chewing muscles grow so vast
下巴便从她的脸上
And from her face Her giant chin
像小提琴一样翘了起来
Sticks out just like a violin
从早到晚嚼口香糖
Chewing, chewing all day long
她年复一年  嚼啊嚼
For years and years she chews away
下颚一天比一天更有力
Her jaws get stronger every day
最后吧嗒咬了一大口
And with one great, tremendous chew
竟咬断了这位小姐的舌头
They bite the poor girl's tongue in two
正是因为这个缘故 我们要尽力...
And that is why we try so hard...
挽救紫罗兰·博雷加德小姐
To save Miss Violet Beauregarde
从早到晚嚼口香糖
Chewing, chewing all day long
Chewing, chewing, chewing, chewing
从早到晚嚼口香糖
Chewing, chewing all day long
旺卡先生!
Mr. Wonka!
把博雷加德小姐滚到船上...
I want you to roll Miss Beauregarde into the boat...
马上带她去榨汁间
and take her along to the Juicing Room at once, okay?
榨汁间?  他们会怎么处理她?
Juicing Room? What are they gonna do to her there?
他们会挤榨她
They're gonna squeeze her.
像挤痘子一样
Like a little pimple.
我们要马上榨干她全身的果汁
We gotta squeeze all that juice out of her immediately.
妈  救我!
Mother, help me.
求求你!
Please.
走吧
Come on.
我们还得赶路呢
Let's boogie.
不坐船要加快脚步才能赶上进度
Without the boat, we'll have to move double-time to keep on schedule.
东西太多会看不完
There's far too much to see.
-旺卡先生?  -恩?
-Mr. Wonka? -Yeah?
你为什么决定让人进来呢?
Why did you decide to let people in?
当然是参观工厂啊
So they could see the factory, of course.
但为何是现在?  为何才五个人?
But why now? And why only five?
大奖是什么?  谁能得到?
What's the special prize, and who gets it?
最特别的大奖是一个惊喜
The best kind of prize is a surprise.
紫罗兰要永远当蓝莓吗?
Will Violet always be a blueberry?
不会  或许吧  我不知道
No. Maybe. I don't know.
但整天嚼口香糖就有这种下场 太恶心了
That's what you get from chewing gum all day. It's disgusting.
你那么讨厌口香糖  做来干嘛?
If you hate gum so much, why do you make it?
我再说一次  别碎碎念 不然我要生气了
Once again, you shouldn't mumble. It's starting to bum me out.
你记得你吃的第一颗糖吗?
Can you remember the first candy you ever ate?
不记得
No.
其实威利·旺卡记得一清二楚 他吃过的第一颗糖果
In fact, Willy Wonka did remember the first candy he ever ate.
(坚果口感 很好吃  余味十足)
对不起  我回想起从前了
I'm sorry, I was having a flashback.
看得出来
I see.
你经常回想从前吗?
These flashbacks happen often?
愈来愈常了...
Increasingly...
就今天
today.
(果仁间)
这个我最了解了
This is a room I know all about.
旺卡先生  我本人是从事坚果业
For you see, Mr. Wonka, I, myself, am in the nut business.
你是用海佛麦四千型来分类吗?
Are you using the Havermax 4000 to do your sorting?
不是
No.
你真是个怪人
You're really weird.
-松鼠  -对  松鼠
-Squirrels. -Yeah. Squirrels.
这些松鼠受过取果仁的特殊训练
These squirrels are specially trained to get the nuts out of shells.
松鼠?  干嘛不用奥柏伦柏人?
Why use squirrels? Why not use Oompa-Loompas?
只有松鼠能完整地取出胡桃果仁
Because only squirrels can get the whole walnut out almost every single time.
它们用指关节轻敲每个胡桃 确定是好或坏
See how they tap them with their knuckles to make sure it's not bad?
你们看
Oh, look. Look.
那个应该是坏坚果
I think that one's got a bad nut.
爸爸  我要一只松鼠
Daddy, I want a squirrel.
抓一只松鼠给我  我要一只
Get me one of those squirrels. I want one.
维露卡  你有很多的宠物了
Veruca, dear, you have many marvelous pets.
我家里只有一匹小马和两条狗
All I've got at home is one pony and two dogs
四只猫 六只小白兔...
and four cats and six bunny rabbits...
两只鹦哥  三只金丝雀 一只绿鹦鹉  一只乌龟...
and two parakeets and three canaries and a green parrot and a turtle...
和一只笨颊鼠 我要一只松鼠!
and a silly old hamster. I want a squirrel!
好吧  爸爸会想办法
All right, pet.
尽快给你一只松鼠
Daddy will get you a squirrel as soon as he possibly can.
我不要普通的松鼠 我要受过训练的松鼠
But I don't want any old squirrel, I want a trained squirrel.
好吧
Very well.
旺卡先生  一只松鼠多少钱?
Mr. Wonka, how much do you want for one of these squirrels?
请你开个价吧
Name your price.
这是非卖品  一只也不能卖
Oh, they're not for sale. She can't have one.
爸爸
Daddy.
对不起  甜心
I'm sorry, darling.
旺卡先生太不讲理了
Mr. Wonka's being unreasonable.
你不给我松鼠  我就自己去抓
If you won't get me a squirrel, I'll get one myself.
维露卡
Veruca.
小女孩?
Little girl?
维露卡  快给我回来啊
Veruca, come back here at once.
维露卡
Veruca.
小女孩
Little girl?
别碰松鼠的坚果
Don't touch that squirrel's nuts.
它会抓狂的
It'll make him crazy.
我就选你吧
I'll have you.
维露卡
Veruca.
不要!
No!
维露卡!
Veruca!
先找到钥匙再说
Let's find the key.
不对  不是这一把
Nope. Not that one.
-爸爸!  -维露卡!
-Daddy! -Veruca!
不对  不是那
No. It's not that one.
找到了
There it is.
找错了
There it isn't.
爸爸  叫它们住手!
Daddy, I want them to stop.
它们在干嘛?
What are they doing?
它们在检查她是不是坏坚果
They're testing to see if she's a bad nut.
天哪  她终究是个坏坚果
Oh, my goodness. She is a bad nut after all.
维露卡!
Veruca!
爸爸!
Daddy!
它们要带她去哪里?
Where are they taking her?
所有坏坚果都要扔进垃圾滑槽
Where all the other bad nuts go. To the garbage chute.
滑槽通往哪里?
Where does the chute go?
通往焚化炉
To the incinerator.
但别担心  只有礼拜二才会焚烧
But don't worry. We only light it on Tuesdays.
今天就是礼拜二
Today is Tuesday.
他们有可能决定今天不焚烧
Well, there's always the chance they decided not to light it today.
说不定她刚掉下去 就卡在滑槽里了
Now, she may be stuck in the chute just below the top.
真是这样  你就伸手拉她出来就好了
If that's the case, all you have to do is just reach in and pull her out.
懂吗?
Okay?
维露卡·索尔特  这个小野蛮
Veruca Salt, the little brute
刚落下了垃圾滑槽
Has just gone down the garbage chute
她沿着垃圾滑槽落到下面
And she will meet, as she descends
将要遇到一班完全不同的朋友
A rather different set of friends
一班完全不同的朋友
比方说  她会遇见一个鱼头
A fish head, for example, cut
这是今天早晨杀的比目鱼
This morning from a halibut
一只煨蚝  已经发臭
An oyster from an oyster stew
一块谁也嚼不动的牛肉
A steak that no one else would chew
还有许许多多别的垃圾
And lots of other things as well
每样都是臭气扑鼻
Each with its rather horrid smell
臭气扑鼻
Horrid smell
这些便是维露卡的新朋友
These are Veruca's newfound friends
等她下去  就会碰头
That she will meet as she descends
这些便是维露卡的新朋友
These are Veruca's newfound friends
到底是谁宠坏她?
Who went and spoiled her, who indeed?
是谁答应她所有的要求?
Who pandered to her every need?
是谁使她变得这样坏?
Who turned her into such a brat?
谁是罪魁祸首?
Who are the culprits?
到底是谁?
Who did that?
说出这话  我实在难过
The guilty ones, now this is sad
罪人就是她亲爱的妈妈和爸爸
Are dear old Mum and loving Dad
真的吗? 太好了
Oh, really? Oh, good.
我刚才得知焚化炉坏掉了
I've just been informed that the incinerator's broken.
所以他们应该会落在垃圾堆上
So there should be about three weeks of rotten garbage to break their fall.
这倒是个好消息
Well, that's good news.
是啊
Yeah.
我们继续走吧
Well, let's keep on trucking.
我怎么没早点想到
I don't know why I didn't think of this.
要在工厂里走动 最快的方法就是搭电梯
The elevator's by far the most efficient way to get around the factory.
不可能有这么多楼层
There can't be this many floors.
你又知道了?  自以为是先生?
How do you know, Mr. Smarty-Pants?
这不是只能上下移动的普通电梯
This isn't just an ordinary up-and-down elevator, by the way.
这电梯可以侧着  纵着  斜着跑...
This elevator can go sideways, longways, slantways...
任何方向都可以
and any other ways you can think of.
只要按下任何按钮 咻一下就到了
You just press any button and, whoosh, you're off.
你们看!
Oh, look. Look.
各位女士先生  欢迎来到软糖山
Ladies and gentlemen, welcome to Fudge Mountain.
这个不提也罢了
I'd rather not talk about this one.
这是木偶医院和烧烫伤中心
This is the Puppet Hospital and Burn Center.
这是新设立的
It's relatively new.
行政办公室
The administration offices.
嗨  桃乐丝
Hello, Doris.
(危险)
为什么这里的一切都毫无意义?
Why is everything here completely pointless?
糖果不需要有意义啊
Candy doesn't have to have a point.
所以才是糖果嘛
That's why it's candy.
太荒谬了
It's stupid.
糖果是在浪费时间
Candy is a waste of time.
我儿子绝对不可能去做巧克力
No son of mine is going to be a chocolatier.
那我逃走算了
Then I'll run away.
逃去瑞士或巴伐利亚
To Switzerland. Bavaria.
全世界的糖果重镇
The candy capitals of the world.
去啊
Go ahead.
等你回来的时  我就不在了
But I won't be here when you come back.
抱歉
Sorry, son.
今晚的营业时间到了
We're closing for the night.
(万国旗展览场)
我要选一个房间
I wanna pick a room.
请便
Go ahead.
(电视间)
拿着
Here.
赶快戴上  无论如何都别摘下来
Put these on quick, and don't take them off whatever you do.
这光线会烧得你眼珠子突出来
This light could burn your eyeballs right out of your skulls.
这种事还是别发生得好  对吧?
And we certainly don't want that, now, do we?
我们在这里测试 我最新最伟大的发明
This is the testing room for my very latest and greatest invention:
电视巧克力糖
Television Chocolate.
有一天我突发奇想
One day it occurred to me:
如果电视能把一张照片
"Hey, if television can break up a photograph...
分解成几百万个小微粒 迅速地在空中传送...
into millions and millions of tiny pieces and send it whizzing through the air...
然后到另一端重新组合...
then reassemble it on the other end...
我何不用巧克力试试看呢?
why can't I do the same with chocolate?
把一块真正的巧克力糖 透过电视传送 伸手就能吃
Why can't I send a real bar of chocolate through the television, ready to be eaten?"
我才不想提  我又不谈那个话题
I'm not gonna touch it. I'm not going in that direction.
好像是不可能的事
Sounds impossible.
本来就不可能
It is impossible.
你对科学一窍不通
You don't understand anything about science.
首先  电波和分子微粒不一样 常识嘛
First off, there's a difference between waves and particles.
其次  将能量转换成物质的动力...
Second, the amount of power it would take to convert energy in matter...
相当于九颗原子弹
would be like nine atomic bombs.
又在碎碎念!
Mumbler!
说真的 你说的话我一个字也听不懂
Seriously, I cannot understand a single word you're saying.
好了
Okey-dokey.
我现在要把一块巧克力糖 从房间的一端...
I shall now send a bar of chocolate from one end of the room...
透过电视传送到另一端
to the other by television.
去拿巧克力来
Bring in the chocolate.
一定要超大才行 因为在电视上...
It's gotta be real big because you know how on TV...
正常人会被拍的变这么小
you can film a regular-size man, and he comes out looking this tall?
这是基本原理
Same basic principle.
不见了
It's gone.
我就说嘛 那块巧克力正从我们头顶上飞过...
Told you. That bar of chocolate is now rushing through the air above our heads...
分解成上百万个小微粒
in a million tiny little pieces.
过来这里  快点 快过来  快啊
Come over here. Come on. Come on. Come on!
看着荧幕
Watch the screen.
出现了
Here it comes.
你们看
Oh, look.
-伸手去拿 -那只是荧幕上的画面啦
-Take it. -It's just a picture on a screen.
胆小鬼
Scaredy-cat.
你拿
You take it.
快去  伸手去拿出来
Go on. Just reach out and grab it.
快点啊
Go on.
我的老天
Holy buckets.
吃吃看  快点
Eat it. Go on.
一定很好吃 那是同一块巧克力
It'll be delicious. It's the same bar.
只是在传送的过程中变小了而已
It's just gotten a little smaller on the journey, that's all.
好好吃哦
It's great.
真是奇迹
It's a miracle.
想像你坐在家里看电视...
So imagine, you're sitting at home watching television...
荧幕上突然出现广告的声音说
and suddenly a commercial will flash onto the screen, and a voice will say:
旺卡巧克力是全世界最好吃的
"Wonka's chocolates are the best in the world.
不相信的话  自己吃吃看
If you don't believe us, try one for yourself."
这时你只要伸手拿起来吃就好了
And you simply reach out and take it.
怎么样?
How about that?
能不能传送别的东西?
So can you send other things?
比如早餐谷片?
Say, like, breakfast cereal?
你知道早餐谷片是什么做的吗?
Do you have any idea what breakfast cereal's made of?
就是削铅笔机里那些卷卷的木屑
It's those little curly wooden shavings you find in pencil sharpeners.
到底能不能透过电视传送出去?
But could you send it by TV if you wanted to?
-当然可以 -人类呢?
-Of course I could. -What about people?
我传送人类干嘛?  反正又不好吃
Well, why would I wanna send a person? They don't taste very good at all.
你不知道你发明了什么吗?  这是传送器耶
Don't you realize what you've invented? It's a teleporter.
这是有史以来最重要的发明
It's the most important invention in the history of the world.
你却满脑子只想着巧克力
And all you think about is chocolate.
冷静点  麦克
Calm down, Mike.
旺卡先生心里有数
I think Mr. Wonka knows what he's talking about.
才怪  他什么也不知道
No, he doesn't. He has no idea.
你认为他是天才  其实他很白痴
You think he's a genius, but he's an idiot.
但我不是白痴
But I'm not.
小男孩
Hey, little boy.
别按我的按钮
Don't push my button.
他不见了
He's gone.
我们去电视那边看看
Let's go check the television, see what we get.
希望别遗漏了他的哪个部位
I sure hope no part of him gets left behind.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
有时候会只传输了其中的一半
Well, sometimes only half of the little pieces find their way through.
若要你选择 你会选你儿子的哪一半?
If you had to choose only one half of your son, which one would it be?
这是什么鸟问题啊?
What kind of a question is that?
没必要发脾气嘛  只是问问而已
No need to snap. Just a question.
每个频道都看看  我开始担心了
Try every channel. I'm starting to feel a little anxious.
-他在那里  -麦克
-There he is. -Mike.
我们至今学会的...
The most important thing...
最重要的事情
That we've ever learned
与孩子们有关的
The most important thing we've learned As far as children are concerned
就是永远不能让他们走近电视机
Is never, never let them near The television set
最好就是根本没有装那个傻玩意
Or better still just don't install The idiotic thing at all
永远不能让他们...
Never, never let them Never, never let them...
Never, never let them...
永远不能让他们...
它腐蚀脑袋
It rots the senses in the head
它把想像力杀掉
It keeps imagination dead
它堵塞人的思想  扰乱人心
It clogs and clutters up the mind
它使小朋友变蠢
It makes a child so dull and blind
好蠢
So dull, so dull
再也不能理解幻想和童话世界
He can no longer understand A fairy tale, a fairyland
童话世界
A fairyland, a fairyland
他的脑子像起司一样软
His brain becomes as soft as cheese
思维能力生锈  凝滞不前
His thinking powers rust and freeze
他不会想  只会看
He cannot think, he only sees
关于麦克·蒂维
Regarding little Mike Teavee
我们感到很抱歉
We very much regret that we
感到很抱歉
Regret that we
我们只好等着看
Shall simply have to wait and see
等着看...
Wait and see, wait and see
Wait and see, wait and see, wait and see
我们感到很抱歉
We very much regret that we
只好等着看
Shall simply have to wait and see
他能否恢复原来的高度
If we can get him back his height
如果不能
But if we can't
也是他自作自受
It serves him right
快抓他出来
Somebody grab him.
救救我
Help me.
谢天谢地  他安然无恙
Oh, thank heavens. He's completely unharmed.
安然无恙? 你在胡说什么?
Unharmed? What are you talking about?
再逆向把我传回去
Just put me back in the other way.
不能逆向了
There is no other way.
这是电视  又不是电话 差别很大耶
It's television, not telephone. There's quite a difference.
你建议我们该怎么做呢?
And what exactly do you propose to do about it?
我不知道
I don't know.
但年轻人的弹性极佳 伸展力超好的
But young men are extremely springy. They stretch like mad.
-把他放进拉太妃糖的机器里 -拉太妃糖的机器?
-Let's go put him in the taffy puller. -Taffy puller?
那是我想到的
Hey, that was my idea.
天哪  他会变得很瘦
Boy, is he gonna be skinny.
是啊
Yeah.
拉太妃糖的机器
Taffy puller.
带蒂维先生和他的...
I want you to take Mr. Teavee and his...
小孩去拉太妃糖的房间
little boy up to the taffy puller, okay?
把他拉长
Stretch him out.
继续参观吧
On with the tour.
还有很多东西要看呢
There's still so much left to see.
现在剩下几个小朋友?
Now, how many children are left?
旺卡先生 只剩下查理一个人了
Mr. Wonka, Charlie's the only one left now.
只剩下你一个人?
You mean, you're the only one?
对
Yes.
其他人都怎么了?
What happened to the others?
亲爱的孩子  这表示你赢了
Oh, my dear boy, but that means you've won.
恭喜你  我衷心祝贺你
Oh, I do congratulate you. I really do.
我太高兴了
I'm absolutely delighted.
我早有预感了  干得好
I had a hunch right from the beginning. Well done.
现在我们刻不容缓
Now, we mustn't dilly or dally.
因为在天黑前还有很多事要做
We have an enormous number of things to do before the day's out.
但幸好有玻璃电梯 可以迅速往来各处...
But luckily for us, we have the great glass elevator to speed things along...
迅速往来各处
Speed things along.
走吧
Come on.
(往上飞出去)
往上飞出去?  这是什么房间?
"Up and Out"? What kind of room is that?
站稳了
Hold on.
我的老天
Oh, my goodness.
我们速度要更快  否则冲不破
We're gonna need to go much faster, otherwise we'll just never break through.
冲破什么?
Break through what?
我多年来一直期待按下那个钮
I've been longing to press that button for years.
走吧  往上飞出去
Well, here we go. Up and out.
-但你真的是要...  -没错
-But do you really mean...? -Yeah. I do.
但这是玻璃做的
But it's made of glass.
玻璃会碎掉啦
It'll smash into a million pieces.
奥古塔斯  请别再吃手指头了
Augustus, please don't eat your fingers.
可是我很好吃耶
But I taste so good.
妈妈  我现在更灵活了耶
Look, Mother. I'm much more flexible now.
对  但变成蓝色了
Yes, but you're blue.
爸爸  我要那种会飞的玻璃电梯
Daddy, I want a flying glass elevator.
维露卡  你今天只能洗个澡 这样就够了
Veruca, the only thing you're getting today is a bath, and that's final.
可是人家要嘛
But I want it.
你住哪里?
Where do you live?
就在那里  那栋小房子
Right over there. That little house.
他们几时会回来?
What time do you think they'll be back?
很难说
Hard to know, dear.
好像有人敲门耶
I think there's someone at the door.
妈妈
Hi, Mom.
妈!  爸!  我们回来了
Mom. Dad. We're back.
-查理!  -查理!
-Charlie. -Charlie.
天哪
Goodness.
这位是威利·旺卡 他送我们回来
This is Willy Wonka. He gave us a ride home.
我看到了
I see that.
你们想必就是这孩子的...
You must be the boy's...
-爸妈?  -对  就是那个
-Parents? -Yeah. That.
他说查理赢得了大奖
He says Charlie's won something.
不只是普通的大奖
Not just some something.
而是有史以来最特别的大奖
The most "something" something of any something that's ever been.
我要把整座工厂送给这个小男孩
I'm gonna give this little boy my entire factory.
你一定是在开玩笑吧
You must be joking.
没有  我是认真的
No, really. It's true.
几个月前在我半年一次的剪发日...
Because you see, a few months ago, I was having my semiannual haircut...
我发现了一件怪事
and I had the strangest revelation.
那根白头发反映出...
In that one silver hair...
我毕生的心血结晶...
I saw reflected my life's work...
我的工厂和亲爱的奥柏伦柏人
my factory, my beloved Oompa-Loompas.
我死了以后谁来照顾他们?
Who would watch over them after I was gone?
当时才我惊觉
I realized in that moment:
我一定要找个继承人
I must find a heir.
我找到了  查理
And I did, Charlie.
就是你
You.
所以你才发出那些金奖卷
That's why you sent out the golden tickets.
奥柏伦柏人是什么?
What are Oompa-Loompas?
我邀请五个小朋友来参观工厂...
I invited five children to the factory...
最不讨人厌的就是最后赢家
and the one who was the least rotten would be the winner.
也就是你  查理
That's you, Charlie.
你意下如何?
So, what do you say?
你要不要抛下这一切 搬来工厂跟我住?
Are you ready to leave all this behind and come live with me at the factory?
好啊
Sure. Of course.
我家人也可以一起去吧?
I mean, it's all right if my family come too?
亲爱的  当然不可以
Oh, my dear boy, of course they can't.
糟老头和臭老太婆成天黏着你...
You can't run a chocolate factory...
怎么经营巧克力工厂?  我无意冒犯
with a family hanging over you like an old, dead goose. No offense.
没关系...混蛋
None taken, jerk.
巧克力制造商要独来独往
A chocolatier has to run free and solo.
他要追逐梦想  不管后果如何
He has to follow his dreams. Gosh darn the consequences.
看看我
Look at me.
我没有家人  却有非凡的成就
I had no family, and I'm a giant success.
若我搬去工厂和你住 我就再也见不到家人了?
So if I go with you to the factory, I won't ever see my family again?
对  算你走运
Yeah. Consider that a bonus.
那我不去了
Then I'm not going.
我说什么也不抛弃家人
I wouldn't give up my family for anything.
就算给我再多巧克力也没用
Not for all the chocolate in the world.
我懂了
Oh, I see.
很奇怪耶
That's weird.
还有别种糖果  不只巧克力
There's other candy too besides chocolate.
对不起  旺卡先生 我要留在这里
I'm sorry, Mr. Wonka. I'm staying here.
好吧  这...
Well, that's just...
出乎我意料之外...
unexpected...
而且很奇怪
and weird.
但我想既然如此  我就...
But I suppose, in that case, I'll just...
再见了
Goodbye, then.
你确定不改变心意?
Sure you won't change your mind?
我确定
I'm sure.
好吧  再见
Okay. Bye.
以后的日子会更好
Things are going to get much better.
终于有一次 乔治娜婆婆知道自己在说什么了
And for once, Grandma Georgina knew exactly what she was talking about.
隔天早上查理帮爸妈 修理屋顶上的破洞
The next morning, Charlie helped his parents fix the hole in the roof.
约瑟夫爷爷不再整天躺在床上
Grandpa Joe spent the whole day out of bed.
他一点也不觉得累
He didn't feel tired at all.
查理的父亲在牙膏工厂 找到一份更好的工作...
Charlie's father got a better job at the toothpaste factory...
修理取代他的机器
repairing the machine that had replaced him.
巴格特一家人日子过得好极了
Things had never been better for the Bucket family.
威利·旺卡就没那么好过了
The same could not be said for Willy Wonka.
我搞不懂
I can't put my finger on it.
糖果向来是我唯一确定的东西...
Candy's the only thing I was ever certain of...
现在我却一点也不确定了
and now I'm just not certain at all.
不知该做什么口味  该试哪个构想
I don't know which flavors to make or which ideas to try.
我开始怀疑自己  太荒谬了
I'm second-guessing myself, which is nuts.
我一直是想做什么糖果就做什么 而我...
I've always made whatever candy I felt like, and I...
就是这样  对吧?
That's just it, isn't it?
我做了想做的糖果 但我现在很沮丧 这表示糖果也很烂
I make the candy I feel like, but now I feel terrible, so the candy's terrible.
你很厉害耶
You're very good.
(灰石咖啡厅)
那个巧克力商很可怜 叫温多还是华特...
Pity about that chocolate fellow, Wendell...Walter.
(旺卡销售量大减)
-威利·旺卡 -就是他
-Willy Wonka. -That's the one.
报上说他的新糖果卖得不太好
Says here in the paper his new candies aren't selling very well.
但我想他可能是个坏蛋 这是他活该
But I suppose maybe he's just a rotten egg who deserves it.
-对啊 -真的吗?
-Yep. -Oh, really?
你见过他?
You ever met him?
我见过
I did.
原本以为他人很好 后来才知道他不是什么好人
I thought he was great at first, but then he didn't turn out so nice.
而且他的发型很奇怪
He also has a funny haircut.
才不呢!
I do not!
-你来干嘛? -我心情不好
-Why are you here? -I don't feel so hot.
你沮丧时要怎样让心情变好?
What makes you feel better when you feel terrible?
和家人在一起
My family.
你对我家人有什么意见?
What do you have against my family?
不只是你的家人 而是想到...
It's not just your family. It's the whole idea of...
他们成天规定你可以怎样 不可以怎样...
They tell you what to do, what not to do...
这样是会扼杀创意的
and it's not conducive to a creative atmosphere.
他们只是想保护你 因为他们爱你
Usually they're just trying to protect you because they love you.
不相信就自己去问啊
If you don't believe me, you should ask.
问谁?  问我爸?
Ask who? My father?
我才不要
No way.
至少不要自己去
At least, not by myself.
你要我陪你去?
You want me to go with you?
好主意 好啊
Hey. Hey, what a good idea. Yeah!
而且我还自备交通...
And you know what? I've got transport...
我得记住玻璃电梯停哪里才行
I have to be more careful where I park this thing.
好像不是这一家耶
I think we've got the wrong house.
(威尔伯·旺卡牙医诊所)
你们有预约吗?
Do you have an appointment?
没有  但他很久没来了
No. But he's overdue.
张开嘴巴
Open.
看看坏了多少牙齿
Now, let's see what the damage is, shall we?
(全球最大的工厂开幕了)
(旺卡在市中心开糖果店)
(旺卡推动地方经济发展)
(工厂开幕了)
天哪
Heavens.
我好久没看过这样的牙齿  自从...
I haven't seen bicuspids like these since...
自从...
Since...
威利?
Willy?
嗨  老爸
Hi, Dad.
这么多年了...
All these years...
你都没用牙线
and you haven't flossed.
一次也没有
Not once.
直到这一天 威利才又向查理提出要求...
It was on this day that Willy Wonka repeated his offer to Charlie...
查理接受了  可是有一个条件
who accepted on one condition.
抱歉晚回来了  我们在脑力激荡
Sorry we're late. We were brainstorming.
都激荡出雷声了
Thought I heard thunder.
-留下来吃晚饭好吗?  -好啊  麻烦你了
-You staying for dinner, Willy? -Yes, please.
我来摆餐具
I'll shuffle the plates.
你身上有花生味
You smell like peanuts.
-我喜欢花生 -谢谢你
-I love peanuts. -Oh, thank you.
你身上有...
You smell like...
老人味  还有肥皂味
old people and soap.
我喜欢
I like it.
手肘别撑在桌上  查理
Elbows off the table, Charlie.
你觉得小覆盆子风筝怎么样?
How do you feel about little raspberry kites?
用甘草根来代替线
With licorice instead of string.
-餐桌上不准谈公事 -对不起
-Boys, no business at the dinner table. -Sorry, Mom.
我觉得你说的没错
I think you're on to something, though, Charlie.
最后 查理·巴格特得到一家巧克力工厂
In the end, Charlie Bucket won a chocolate factory.
但威利·旺卡得到了更好的礼物
But Willy Wonka got something even better:
那就是家人
A family.
有一件事可以非常确定
And one thing was absolutely certain:
甜美的人生莫过于此
Life had never been sweeter.